Charles B. Davenport Papers ca.1903-1940 Mss.B.D27
American Philosophical Society
Charles Benedict Davenport Papers
1874-1946
Mss.B.D27
American Philosophical Society
63.0 Linear feet
Founded by the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences in 1890, the Biological Laboratory at Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y., was little more than a languishing outpost until the arrival of Charles B. Davenport in 1898. Over the course of two decades, the ambitious young biologist used his extraordinary administrative skills to transform the institution into the premier center of eugenical study and, as its director, to position himself as the leading spokesman for eugenical research in North America. The Davenport Papers (ca. 43 lin. feet) is a large and nearly comprehensive body of correspondence, lectures, diaries (1878-1942, mostly brief entries of an uneven character), student notebooks and family correspondence pertaining to Charles Davenport and the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. The collection is divided into two series, the Charles Davenport Papers, which provides valuable documentation of the development of American biology, animal and plant genetics, and eugenics during the period 1898-1942, with some perspective on the international eugenics movement. Series II, the Cold Spring Harbor Records (ca.20 lin. feet), consists largely of administrative correspondence relating to the laboratory, including Davenport's correspondence with Carnegie administrators (esp. Robert Woodward and John Merriam), accounts and reports concerning financial matters, publications, salaries, material relative to the early history of Cold Spring Harbor labs, and records relative to the numerous professional assistants who worked under Davenport. Among the major correspondents are the American Breeders Association, Committee on Eugenics; American Eugenics Society; American Society of Naturalists; Committee on a Study of the American Negro; Galton Society (see also the extensive correspondence with William K. Gregory); Eugenics Education Society (see Mrs. S. Gotto correspondence); International Congresses of Eugenics; International Federation of Eugenic Organizations, Committee on Race Crossing; National Committee on Mental Hygiene; National Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor; and the Pan-American Conference on Eugenics and Homiculture. There are correspondence and papers relating to the Station for Experimental Evolution, the Eugenics Record Office, and the Carnegie Institution of Washington, and a substantial series relating to a long-range study of children carried out at Letchworth Village, Thiles, New York.
Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944
Scope and Contents note
The Charles B. Davenport Papers contains the professional correspondence of one of America's best known eugenicists during the period 1915 to 1935. Documenting all phases of Davenport's life and career, the collection is an invaluable resource for study of the history of the eugenics movement in America, the history of genetics, biometrics, and evolutionary thought during the early 20th century, and the history of the Biological Laboratory, the Carnegie Institution Department of Genetics, and the Eugenics Record Office at Cold Spring Harbor.
The collection is divided into two series, each arranged alphabetically:
Series I. Correspondence, 1878-1944 (43 linear feet)
Series II. Cold Spring Harbor Series, 1899-1946 (20 linear feet)
Administrative Correspondence, 1899-1939
Records of Assistants, 1904-1946
Photographs, 1900-1936
Bibliography
E. Carleton MacDowell, "Charles Benedict Davenport, 1866-1944: A study in conflicting influences," Bios 17 (1946), 3-50.
African American History Note
Of interest to researchers of African American history and culture will be Davenport's activities in the fields of genetics (especially eugenics), which are documented in his personal and professional correspondence and by his activities on such committees as the Committee on the Study of the American Negro.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Scholars of physiology, biochemistry, or biophysics may be interested in the following materials:
Series I. Charles B. Davenport Papers:
Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947 ( Includes correspondence regarding biochemistry; poultry genetics; Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole; Carnegie Institution of Washington; conferences; displaced German scholars.) Correspondence (5 folders (137 items)) 1898-1937 English
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987 Correspondence (4 items) 1934-1935 English
Series II. Cold Spring Harbor Series:
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory of Quantitative Biology, New York ( Correspondence, reports, accounts, and other records relating to operation of the various laboratories at Cold Spring Harbor.) Records (20 linear feet) 1899-1946 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
The scientific path of Frank Rattray Lillie began around 1890 at the University of Chicago. Starting with descriptive morphology of cell lineage of the fresh water mussel, his research moved progressively toward an experimental, physiological, and biochemical approach to fertilization and differentiation. From 1910 to 1921 Lillie focused mainly on physiological studies of fertilization in sea urchins, work which culminated in his noted "fertilizin" theory. During that period he also began his studies of sexual differentiation in freemartins, research that led him to collaborate with biochemists and resulted in the isolation and chemical analyses of sex hormones. Under Lillie's leadership, sex research -- the physiological and biochemical studies of differentiation, development, and maturation -- became a major program at the University of Chicago.
Lillie was an ardent promoter of experimental biology and general physiology. His scientific success extended far beyond the laboratory. Under his directorship (1910-1935) the biology division at the University of Chicago flourished, and his fifty-five years of leadership at the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole were crucial to that institution's development. Lillie was an influential figure in the National Academy of Sciences and the National Research Council, and helped shape the direction of the life sciences through his advisory role in the Carnegie and Rockefeller Foundations.
Related Archival Materials note
The Records of the Eugenics Record Office (Ms Coll 77) and the American Eugenics Society (575.06 Am3) complement the Davenport Papers.
The APS contains the collections of a number of associates of Davenport's, including his former students H. S. Jennings (B J44) and Sewall Wright (Ms Coll 60), his successors at Cold Spring Harbor, Albert F. Blakeslee (B B585) and Milislav Demerec (B D394), and several of his contemporaries.
Separated Materials note
Davenport's death mask has been removed for storage.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1965.
Other Finding Aids note
The printed version of Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the American Philosophical Society contains a further description of the Davenport Papers and includes a detailed biography of Charles Davenport.
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Brooklyn Heights, N.Y., one year after the end of the Civil War, Charles Davenport was raised under the stern and often distant eye of his father, Amzi Benedict Davenport, an elder in the Congregational Church, a former abolitionist and temperance man. Strict, even Puritanical, Amzi Davenport raised his son for a practical career, educating Charles at home until he was 13, and using him as his office boy. In contrast, Charles' mother, Jane Joralemon Dimon, was warm and affectionate, and encouraged Charles' youthful interest in the decidedly unpractical study of nature.
After graduating from Brookyln Polytechnic Institute, Charles accepted an eminently practical job as surveyor for nine months,largely to please his father. His interests, however, lay with the natural sciences, and determined to make a career for himself in science, he entered Harvard to study zoology. A superior and disciplined student, he spent his summers at the Marine Biological Station at Woods Hole and at Agassiz's Laboratory at Newport, R.I., continuing directly from study for his bachelor's degree onto his doctorate.
After receiving his PhD in 1892, Davenport was selected by the Department of Zoology to remain as instructor. Although his tenure was relatively brief, it was highly productive. Among his students were number of promising young scientists including E. B. Castle and Herbert Spencer Jennings, and gained an intimate familiarity with a range of quantitative and statistical techniques that provided a basis for his later work in biomety. Perhaps more importantly, he gained his first taste of scientific fame when he transformed the notes for the first course he taught at Harvard into a textbook, Experimental Morphology (N.Y., 1897, 1899) that was both well received and widely read. In 1904, he published an equally successful manual on quantitative methods in laboratory sciences, Statistical Methods with Special Reference to Biological Variation. Yet the most important thing to emerge from his Harvard days, professionally and personally, was his marriage in 1894 to Gertrude Crotty, a graduate student from Kansas who became his collaborator on a number of projects as his career took off.
In 1898, Davenport was appointed Director of the summer programs at Cold Spring Harbor, and in the following year he accepted a position on the faculty of the University of Chicago. Quickly rising to Assistant Professor (1901), Davenport hatched a number of schemes in Chicago with the intent to organize a laboratory devoted to the integration of physics, chemistry, and physiology into experimental evolutionary biology. His timing could not have been better: with the rediscovery of Mendel's theory of inheritance in 1900, he was poised to take advantage of a reinvigorated discipline, and although he was at first unconvinced by Mendelian theory, he recognized its value for coordinating research for the new laboratory. From early on, he was drawn particularly to applying genetic theory to the "betterment" of human populations. Seeing himself as building upon the work of Francis Galton, the man who had coined the word eugenics in 1883, Davenport explicitly sought to unveil the scientific basis for the inheritance of physical, mental, and moral characteristics in human populations with the goal of eventually breeding better humans.
Davenport's break was not long in coming. On a visit to London in 1902, he had met Galton and the pioneering biometrician, Karl Pearson, both of whom helped refine his plans for the Cold Spring Harbor laboratory, and who helped quicken his faith in Mendelian genetics. More importantly, in that same year, the establishment of the Carnegie Institution of Washington provided Davenport with a likely source for funding the state of the art genetics laboratory for which he longed. When his detailed plans for the lab were approved by Carnegie in 1904, he resigned from his position at Chicago and took up the reins at Cold Spring Harbor full time.
In 1910, Davenport approached Mrs. E. H. Harriman for funds to establish yet another link in the Cold Spring empire, the Eugenics Record Office. With the publication of his Heredity in Relation to Eugenics (New York, 1911) in the following year, Davenport's position at the apex of American eugenics was assured. Although his quantitative skills began increasingly to lag behind those of his peers, and although many of his publications were considered slapdash, he sat in the center of the most powerful research facility in the nation, and he was successful at nurturing younger scientists, incluidng G. H. Shull, Albert F. Blakeslee, and Milislav Demerec, among others. At the same time, his second in command in the Eugenics Record Office, H. H. Laughlin, became a spokesman for the programmatic side of the eugenics movement, lobbying for eugenic legislation to restrict immigration and sterilize "defectives," educating the public on eugenic health, and disseminating eugenic ideas widely. The Record Office formally came under the aegis of the Carnegie Institution of Washington in 1918.
Davenport's 1929 work, Race Crossing in Jamaica (1929), coauthored with Morris Steggerda, represented the apogee of his influence. Based on anthropometric measures of body dimensions, skin color, and hair type, the study was vehemently attacked by geneticists for Davenport's simplistic attempts to link mental capacity and race and for his failure to account for environmental and cultural influences. In many ways, his career after 1929 is one of steady decline. Davenport remained at the helm in Cold Spring Harbor until his retirement in 1942, and died in 1944.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Adams, Charles Christopher Correspondence (77 items) 1899-1932
Agassiz, Alexander Correspondence (8 items) 1899-1908
American Association for the Advancement of Science. Committee on Bibliography of Science Correspondence (69 items) 1910-1923
American Association for the Advancement of Science. Darwin Anniversary Committee Correspondence (8 folders) 1907-1914
American Eugenics Society Records (114 items) 1925-1933, 1958
American Philosophical Society Correspondence (164 items) 1907-1932
Andrus, Margaret Correspondence (109 items) 1920-1925
Atkins, Charles D. Correspondence (287 items) 1914-1924
Babcock, Ernest Brown Correspondence (41 items) 1913-1930
Bacon, Robert Low Correspondence (50 items) 1923-1933
Baker, Benjamin W. Correspondence (62 items) 1921-1929
Balch, Francis Noyes Correspondence (59 items) 1897-1934
Banker, Howard J. Correspondence (125 items) 1914-1950
Banta, Arthur M. Correspondence (370 items) 1903-1946
Barker, Lewellys Franklin Correspondence (73 items) 1900-1933
Barrows, Florence Correspondence (60 items) 1927-1931
Bateson, William N. Correspondence (77 items) 1904-1928
Bell, Alexander Graham Correspondence (162 items) 1904-1929
Belling, John Correspondence (40 items) 1916-1940
Benedict, Francis Gano Correspondence (114 items) 1907-1933
Benedict, Ralph Curtiss Correspondence (90 items) 1920-1932
Bernstein, Felix Correspondence (27 items) 1923-1938
Bigelow, Maurice Alpheus Correspondence (50 items) 1898-1929
Blakeslee, Albert Francis Correspondence (390 items) 1900-1943
Boas, Franz Correspondence (86 items) 1899-1933
Bosanquet, Barbara S. Correspondence (130 items) 1929-1932
Brown, Leland A. Correspondence (58 items) 1919-1951
Bumpus, Hermon Carey Correspondence (54 items) 1891-1915
Byrnes, Esther F. Correspondence (83 items) 1916-1940
Campbell, Clarence Gorden Correspondence (53 items) 1927-1932
Cannon, Walter Bradford Correspondence (45 items) 1896-1934
Carnegie Institution of Washington Records (85 folders) 1909-1932
Carnegie Institution of Washington. Gilbert, Walter M. Correspondence (32 folders) 1927-1939
Cartledge, J. Lincoln Correspondence (86 items) 1919-1946
Castle, William Ernest Correspondence (323 items) 1893-1940
Cattell, James McKeen Correspondence (366 items) 1898-1931
Colby, Frank Moore Correspondence (68 items) 1900-1902
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Records (9 folders) 1902-1940
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory -- Beginnings Correspondence (49 items) 1902-1904
Cold Spring Harbor. Station for Experimental Evolution Correspondence (3 folders) 1911-1924
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. Station for Experimental Evolution Records (16 folders) 1904-1923
Cole, Leon Jacob Correspondence (66 items) 1906-1929
Concilium Bibliographicum Correspondence (97 items) 1904-1932
Conklin, Edwin Grant Correspondence (284 items) 1896-1931
Cook, Robert Carter Correspondence (65 items) 1922-1931
Cori, Carl J. Correspondence (22 items) 1891-1930
Corner, George Washington Correspondence (61 items) 1919-1939
Cowdry, Edmund Vincent Correspondence (49 items) 1926-1931
Crampton, Charles Ward Correspondence (100 items) 1918-1933
Crampton, Henry Edward Correspondence (104 items) 1904-1925
Danforth, Charles Haskell Correspondence (58 items) 1909-1942
Darwin, Leonard Correspondence (148 items) 1921-1937
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Abstracts Manuscripts (45 items) 1923-1933
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Autobiography Manuscripts (40 items) 1916-1940
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Book reviews Manuscripts (44 items) 1913-1944
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Diaries Diaries (97 items) 1878-1943
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Experimental Evolution Lectures Manuscripts (2 folders) 1902-1903
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Harvard Days Correspondence (33 items) 1887-1939
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Harvard Research Manuscripts (7 folders) 1891-1892
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Heredity Lectures, Universtiy of Chicago Manuscripts (2 folders) 1901
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Lectures Manuscripts (148 items) 1902-1934
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Scrapbook, 75th Birthday Scrapbooks (6 folders) 1941
Davenport, Charles Benedict -- Twins Manuscripts (5 folders) n.d.
Davenport, Gertrude C. Correspondence (758 items) 1893-1943
Davenport, William E. Correspondence (91 items) 1883-1943
Davis, Bradley Moore Correspondence (41 items) 1904-1927
Davis, Nelson Fithian Correspondence (57 items) 1890-1909
Day, Arthur Louis Correspondence (62 items) 1913-1921
DeForest, Henry W. Correspondence (3 folders) 1907-1931
Demerec, Milislav Correspondence (112 items) 1921-1944
Dewey, John Correspondence (7 items) 1901-1917
Donaldson, Henry Herbert Correspondence (118 items) 1897-1929
Draper, John William Correspondence (88 items) 1915-1931
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Correspondence (57 items) 1919-1942
DuPont, A. F. Correspondence (41 items) 1930-1933
Earle, Mabel L. Correspondence (18 folders) 1914-1935
East, Edward Murray Correspondence (40 items) 1905-1931
Eigenmann, Carl H. Correspondence (74 items) 1891-1926
Emerson, Rollins Adams Correspondence (27 items) 1907-1930
Estabrook, Arthur H. Correspondence (259 items) 1911-1932
Eugenical News Correspondence (30 folders) 1916-1933
Eugenics and Genetics in Colleges Manuscripts (6 folders) 1919-1920
Eugenics Education Society (Great Britain) Correspondence (69 items) 1923-1931
Eugenics Record Office Records (43 folders) 1910-1937
Eugenics Research Association Records (10 folders) 1914-1932
Fairchild, David G. Correspondence (61 items) 1904-1929
Fischer, Eugen Correspondence (51 items) 1908-1933
Fish, Harold D. Correspondence (150 items) 1916-1932
Fisher, Irving Correspondence (462 items) 1909-1933
Fisk, Eugene L. Correspondence (116 items) 1914-1927
Forbes, Stephen Alfred Correspondence (52 items) 1895-1928
Frassetto, Fabio Correspondence (74 items) 1919-1933
Frink, Lillian B. Correspondence (112 items) 1930-1935
Gager, C. Stuart Correspondence (141 items) 1907-1943
Galton Society Correspondence (3 folders) 1918-1927
Gates, Reginald Ruggles Correspondence (69 items) 1909-1932
Gerould, John H. Correspondence (90 items) 1894-1928
Gies, William J. Correspondence (119 items) 1904-1927
Gilbert, Walter M. -- Carnegie Institution of Washington Correspondence (321 items) 1905-1926
Gini, Corrado Correspondence (111 items) 1923-1933
Glaser, Otto Correspondence (45 items) 1916-1920
Goddard, Henry H. Correspondence (148 items) 1909-1921
Goethe, C. M. Correspondence (50 items) 1924-1930
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict Correspondence (22 items) 1914-1933
Goodale, Hubert Dana Correspondence (86 items) 1911-1933
Gortner, Ross Aiken Correspondence (96 items) 1909-1941
Gotto, Sybil Correspondence (103 items) 1910-1923
Gould, Charles W. Correspondence (47 items) 1921-1931
Gould, Joseph F. Correspondence (48 items) 1913-1916
Govaerts, Albert P. Correspondence (83 items) 1921-1931
Grant, Madison Correspondence (247 items) 1904-1933
Greenman, Milton J. Correspondence (71 items) 1906-1932
Gregory, William K. Correspondence (560 items) 1912-1933
Grier, Norman MacDowell Correspondence (65 items) 1914-1934
Harriman, Mrs. E. H. Correspondence (7 folders) 1910-1932
Harrington, C. L. Correspondence (72 items) 1906-1909
Harris, J. Arthur Correspondence (370 items) 1901-1930
Harris, Reginald G. Correspondence (60 items) 1919-1923
Harrison, Ross G. Correspondence (247 items) 1903-1933
Hays, Willet Martin Correspondence (494 items) 1902-1924
Hektoen, Ludvig Correspondence (158 items) 1924-1932
Henshaw, Samuel Correspondence (63 items) 1896-1922
Herwerden, Marianne A. van Correspondence (86 items) 1920-1934
Hoffman, Frederick L. Correspondence (104 items) 1917-1933
Henry Holt and Company Correspondence (6 folders) 1909-1938
Hooper, Franklin W. Correspondence (113 items) 1899-1914
Hooton, Earnest Albert Correspondence (59 items) 1918-1935
Howard, Leland Ossian Correspondence (124 items) 1899-1923
Hrdlicka, Ales Correspondence (277 items) 1906-1936
Hughes, Roscoe D. Correspondence (72 items) 1929-1934
Hunt, Harrison R. Correspondence (125 items) 1915-1940
International Congress of Eugenics. Third Congress Records (12 folders) 1930-1933
International Congress of Genetics. Sixth Congress Records (10 folders) 1928-1932
International Federation of Eugenics Organizations Records (33 folders) 1924-1936
Jelliffe, Smith Ely Correspondence (136 items) 1893-1936
Jenkins, George B. Correspondence (85 items) 1912-1929
Jennings, Herbert Spencer Correspondence (124 items) 1897-1931
Johnson, Duncan S. Correspondence (77 items) 1898-1932
Johnson, Roswell H. Correspondence (197 items) 1897-1936
Johnstone, E. R. Correspondence (75 items) 1909-1931
Jones, Donald F. Correspondence (3 folders) 1919-1935
Jones, Townsend Correspondence (61 items) 1901-1915
Jordan, David S. Correspondence (124 items) 1895-1926
Jordan, H. E. Correspondence (69 items) 1906-1931
Just, Gunther Correspondence (21 items) 1921-1930
Kellogg, John Harvey Correspondence (156 items) 1912-1930
Kellogg, Vernon Lyman Correspondence (92 items) 1895-1929
Key, Wilhelmine E. Correspondence (96 items) 1901-1932
Kidder, Alfred Vincent Correspondence (57 items) 1926-1933
Laanes, Alice Gould Correspondence (72 items) 1925-1946
Laughlin, Harry Hamilton Correspondence (1,154 items) 1907-1946
Lenz, Fritz Correspondence (27 items) 1923-1931
Letchworth Village -- Humphreys, Edward J. Correspondence (342 items) 1933-1941
Letchworth Village -- Little, Charles S. Correspondence (214 items) 1913-1936
Lillie, Frank Rattray Correspondence (137 items) 1898-1937
Little, Clarence Cook Correspondence (321 items) 1916-1934
Livingston, Burton E. Correspondence (52 items) 1907-1930
Loeb, Jacques Correspondence (13 items) 1892-1919
Lundborg, Herman B. Correspondence (55 items) 1913-1936
Lutz, Anna Mae Correspondence (102 items) 1904-1921
Lutz, Frank E. Correspondence (113 items) 1901-1935
MacDougal, Daniel Trembly Correspondence (187 items) 1899-1930
MacDowell, E. Carleton Correspondence (146 items) 1909-1929
McGraw, Myrtle B. Correspondence (6 folders) 1933-1936
Mark, Edward Laurens Correspondence (236 items) 1889-1943
Martz, Eugene W. Correspondence (157 items) 1929-1933
Mayor, Alfred G. Correspondence (214 items) 1895-1926
Merriam, John C. Correspondence (1,786 items) 1918-1940
Metz, Charles W. Correspondence (491 items) 1912-1936
Milles, Bess Lloyd Correspondence (111 items) 1923-1936
Mjoen, Jon Alfred Correspondence (115 items) 1916-1936
Morgan, Ann H. Correspondence (59 items) 1915-1930
Morgan, Thomas Hunt Correspondence (279 items) 1893-1931
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (22 items) 1918-1932
Muncey, Elizabeth B. Correspondence (84 items) 1911-1925
Murphy, Robert Cushman Correspondence (71 items) 1914-1936
National Academy of Sciences -- Candidates for Election Records (3 folders) 1916-1930
Nelson, Anna Louise Correspondence (106 items) 1917-1929
Osborn, Frederick Henry Correspondence (183 items) 1928-1942
Osborn, Henry Fairfield Correspondence (326 items) 1902-1933
Parker, George Howard Correspondence (99 items) 1889-1935
Paton, Stewart Correspondence (83 items) 1911-1931